<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-28T14:35:41+00:00</updated><id>https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Community Creativity 4 Development</title><subtitle>Connecting communities while finding solutions to protect the environment from global warming.</subtitle><author><name>CC4D</name></author><entry><title type="html">A Deeper Look at CC4D</title><link href="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/2023-03-21-repair-culture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Deeper Look at CC4D" /><published>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/repair-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/2023-03-21-repair-culture/">&lt;p&gt;
  Community Creativity for Development (CC4D) is a youth-led community based organization in the Eden Rhino Camp Refugee Settlement in the west Nile region of Uganda with the aim to connect communities while also protecting the environment from global warming. We do this through organizing repair café events that encourage people to work together and share knowledge and skills which helps to bring people together and work on building a more coherent and peaceful community.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  CC4D was started in 2019 by three refugee youths (&lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mathew-lubari-18468a102/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Mathew Lubari&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dawa-edina-b75161168/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Edina Dawa&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/maliamungu-richard-5b14b114b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Maliamungu Richard&lt;/a&gt;) with a few tools at their disposal, such as zip-lock ties, one screwdriver, a cutter, and a toothbrush. Today the team consists of 4 staff members and over 15 volunteers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;How did CC4D come to be?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We were identified by the &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://therestartproject.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Restart Project&lt;/a&gt; after Mathew made a comment on their Facebook page, asking for support to establish a repair café center. Ugo, the co-founder and co-director of the Restart Project, responded and we had our first meeting in October 2021.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  In November 2021, &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/ugo-vallauri-b814684/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Ugo Vallauri&lt;/a&gt; nominated Mathew to receive flash grants worth $5000 from the ShuttleWorth foundation to support CC4D repair activities and in December 2021, Mathew was featured in the &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://therestartproject.org/podcast/refugee-repair/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Restart Project Podcast&lt;/a&gt; where he talked about his goals for CC4D.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The Restart Project later introduced us to the &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://talk.restarters.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Restarters Group&lt;/a&gt;, where I learnt more about how repair contributes to the planet’s well-being, networked, and met friends like Rebecca Gonzalez Leon, who introduced us to &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jessika-luth-richter-7ba09b2b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Jessika Richter&lt;/a&gt; of Repair Cafe Malmo Where. She reached out to &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://www.ifixit.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Ifixit&lt;/a&gt; and helped CC4D receive a business tool kit and helped us get exposure. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Why are we interested in repair culture?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  As an IT technician by profession(Mathew), I love repairing stuff and was inspired by my dad, who is a medical personnel but also loves repairing things. I remember watching him repairing his watch and radio and was impressed. Additionally in early 2013 I was upset when I got locked out of my phone and could not access apps and did not know how to fix the problem. So I took my phone to a technician, but was not allowed to watch while he repaired it. I went out, but stood in a place where I could see how he was fixing the problem. After I paid him, I set out to learn how to do this myself. I succeeded in locking and unlocking it. Later, my laptop broke down and couldn&apos;t power on, so I took it to a technician who tried fixing it but failed. But instead of giving me back my laptop in good shape, he had removed some of the parts like the hard drive disk, RAM, and the network card. Only after taking it to an Indian technician did I learn that these parts had been removed. Understandably, this angered me and it also made me want to learn and be able to teach people how to repair things and make repair open, which includes teaching them to be ethical while providing repair services.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Edina Dawa&lt;/b&gt;  loves repair and was inspired to continue to learn about and offer tech repair services while doing her internship with the Community Technology Empowerment Network (CTEN), a refugee led organization providing tech services in the Rhino camp, where I was working as the IT assistant in their Refugee information center (RIC).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Richard Maliamungu&lt;/b&gt; was a close neighbor while we were in Yei South Sudan and we happened to live in the camp while in the refugee camp. He asked Mathew for career guidance, especially what to do after completing his high school. He was stuck making a decision but I welcomed him to join the repair movement starting as a helper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;Mathew&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;Edina&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;Richard&lt;/b&gt; have been beneficiaries of the r0g_agency since 2018, when we first participated in a four week training on as part of their #ASKnet (Access to Skills Knowledge and Network) training, which is funded by the BMZ. This training was the first ever repair café event to be held in the Rhino camp and Uganda at large and it was when we realized that the community needed the repair services, because the turn out of community members coming for repairs was very large.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We were also introduced to the #ASKotec: Access to Skills and Knowledge open tech emergency case. The &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://openculture.agency/outcomes/askotec/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;#ASKotec&lt;/a&gt; is a kit that is designed to work as a mobile training set and is equipped with the items needed to teach others how to use Open Tech and Open Source Hardware in order to innovate, educate, and repair items, thereby providing access to vital skills and knowledge. The kit is especially valuable to communities where access to tools and materials is often scarce. The Open Tech Emergency Case is housed in a rugged, dust-proof case and includes a range of high-quality tools and materials needed to teach hands-on skills in terms of repairs, development, and upcycling. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Currently we are members of and lead experts in the &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://lead.asknet.community/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;#ASKnet community&lt;/a&gt; directory, &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://globalinnovationgathering.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Global Innovation Gathering&lt;/a&gt; (GIG), &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://afriicaosh.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Africa Open Science Hardware&lt;/a&gt; (AfricaOSH), &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://africamakerspace.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Africa Makers Space Network&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://talk.restarters.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Restarters community&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;https://forum.openhardware.science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Global Open Science Hardware&lt;/a&gt; (GOSH). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We have established a community repair café center (Bright Makerspace) in Eden zone, Rhino Camp refugee settlement, Uganda. This is a platform for skills training, learning, mentorship and e-waste management (offer repair services Monday to Friday and provide access to tools and information to anyone in the community) and where community members bring, on a daily basis their broken/faulty and damaged items/belongings to be fixed by local experts (volunteers) in repair of electronics, electrical, mechanical and textile products. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Above all, we conduct repair café events that encourage people to work together and share knowledge and skills which helps to bring people together and work on building a more coherent and peaceful community
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Achievements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  CC4D has so far trained 50 young people (28 men and 22 women), giving them hands-on repair skills. 12 women have also been mentored on online safety. 5 men and 5 women leaders from 5 Refugee-led organizatios have also learned about digital communication tools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We have held 10 repair cafe events (2021  - 2022), where we have fixed around 550 items such as solar lanterns, torches, mobile phones, radios, bicycles, clothes, and footwear. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We have also provided awareness to over 2,000 refugee and host communities about the value and importance of repair and the dangers of poor disposal of electronic waste. Over 1,000 refugees and host communities accessed repair tools, information and technical support and 300 electronics waste items have been collected. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  CC4D became the first organization to celebrate International Repair Day in Uganda in 2021 and in 2022 it organized a public event that brought together community members, UN Agencies, and humanitarian organizations to celebrate International Repair Day. The event was meant to popularize the International Repair Day and communicate the value and importance of repairing things. This event was organized using funds from crowdfunding, with much support coming from the repair café Malmö, where 10,000 Swedish Krona (about 900 euros/USD) was collected.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Currently our challenge is that our space is small, has only a few tools, and lack means of transport to reach far areas. And most of all we lack funding. We do not have a project that is funded and rely mostly on support from individuals and friends.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Our future plans are to have a mobile van for repair café outreach, set up repair café centers in the 6 zones of the Rhino camp and other settlements within Uganda, and expand to South Sudan. 
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Mathew Lubari</name></author><summary type="html">Community Creativity for Development (CC4D) is a youth-led community based organization in the Eden Rhino Camp Refugee Settlement in the west Nile region of Uganda with the aim to connect communities while also protecting the environment from global warming. We do this through organizing repair café events that encourage people to work together and share knowledge and skills which helps to bring people together and work on building a more coherent and peaceful community.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">E-Waste Awareness</title><link href="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/2023-03-09-e-waste-awareness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="E-Waste Awareness" /><published>2023-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/e-waste-awareness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mrponuk.github.io/CC4D/posts/2023-03-09-e-waste-awareness/">&lt;p&gt;The increasing levels of e-waste, and improper and unsafe treatment, and disposal through incineration or in landfills pose significant challenges to the environment and human health in refugee settlements in the West-Nile region of Uganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Items such as Solar Lamps, Mobile Phones and Radios have been increasingly owned by refugees as primary sources of communication, access to information and lighting at night. However, as devices break down, the demand for the repair and maintenance of those devices is high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, there is just one project organized by IOM, focusing on waste related to solar lamps (Sun bell) in Bidibidi refugee settlement. Still, there were no partners delivering/organizing repair services/cafes to raise awareness on e-waste and repair a wide range of different electronic devices. A report from GPA and UNITAR (Electronic-waste) Management for Off- grid Solar Solutions in Displacement Settings, January, 2022 highlights that E-waste management practices in displacement settings are not present or sufficient in eliminating or reducing health and environmental hazards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;What has CC4D done from 2021 - 2022?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CC4D has been providing repair services through repair café events and training to the refugee youths on e-waste management(repair, reuse and upcycling) aimed at creating awareness on safe disposal of electronics products within rhino camp refugee settlement. We have trained 50(29 males and 21 females) as electronics repair technicians, organized 10 repair cafe&apos;s(upto 500 electronics items repaired) and sensitized over 500 refugees and host communities on e-waste management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenges faced:&lt;br&gt;
1- There is still a huge amount of broken items in hands of the refugees and host communities,&lt;br&gt;
2- Logistical challenges (we could not manage to reach villages which are very far).&lt;br&gt;
3- Lack of enough tools and no spare parts.&lt;br&gt;
4- Lack of sufficient electricity at the CC4D repair café center.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;What is the need now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a need for more awareness concerning the repair, reuse, recycling and disposal of electronics products within rhino camp refugee communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that your support will greatly create an impact in rhino camp refugee settlement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wish to support, email on &lt;a class=&quot;text-decoration-none text-primary&quot; href=&quot;mailto:info@cc4duganda.org&quot;&gt;info@cc4duganda.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>CC4D</name></author><summary type="html">The increasing levels of e-waste, and improper and unsafe treatment, and disposal through incineration or in landfills pose significant challenges to the environment and human health in refugee settlements in the West-Nile region of Uganda.</summary></entry></feed>